Guide to the Ernestine Evans Papers, 1890-1968
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Ernestine Evans Papers, 1890-1968
[Bulk Dates: 1930-1967].
Evans, Ernestine, 1889-1967.
13 linear ft. (28 boxes, 24 document boxes, 2 oversized boxes, 2 index card boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0405
4078744
Contained in this collection are documents related to the life and career of Ernestine Evans, a journalist, critic and literary agent active in the early-to-mid-twentieth century. Personal and professional correspondence and a wide variety of literary manuscripts, likely accumulated during her long career as a literary agent, constitute the bulk of this collection. In addition, the collection includes photographs, drawings and other visual material. Also represented in this collection are clippings of Evans' and other journalists' work; printed material, both periodicals and books; personal documents (including address books, contact lists and journals), financial documents and medical documents.
Biographical Note
Ernestine Evans was a prolific female journalist, author, editor and literary agent active in the early-to-mid twentieth century.
Evans was born in Omaha, Nebraska in 1889. The first of two children born to Arthur and Allie Evans (her brother, Ward, was born in 1893). Looking back on her childhood, she would later write that her family rarely lived in the same dwelling for more than a year at a time. Evans' father, a lawyer, had difficulty finding steady work, and her mother was seriously ill for much of Evans' early life; she died when Evans was 16 years old.
Evans matriculated at the University of Chicago around 1908, where she undertook a Bachelor of Philosophy degree, specializing in English and Economics and taking a journalism course led by the sociologist George Edgar Vincent.
It was also during her college years that Evans's career as a journalist began in earnest. During the latter two years of her degree, Evans served as Assistant to the Editor of the university's Astrophysical Journal, and her boss, also the University of Chicago's Dean of Science, Henry Gordon Gale, gave her an uncommon degree of freedom with this post: in addition to extensive fact-checking and other quotidian duties, Evans was often given the opportunity to write articles for the Journal under Gale's name.
Upon graduating in 1912, Evans found a job at the Chicago Inter Ocean, a daily newspaper aimed at an elite readership. Initially Evans was charged with writing articles for the paper's Sunday features pages, but she was soon promoted and became the assistant to the Inter Ocean's political editor. With this position, she covered the suffrage movement, and traveled to Washington on assignment. Evans' time at the Inter Ocean was cut short, however: the newspaper folded not long after she joined its ranks. With this job lost, Evans found a job as assistant editor at the New York Press, a daily penny paper with a reputation for "yellow" journalism. Evans remained at this job for about a year.
Evans was offered an assignment for The Independent, a weekly journal based in Boston, which would require her to travel to Eastern Europe to cover prohibition in Russia. Evans was not offered any travel money for the assignment, but she had some leftover pay from previous writing jobs, and so she set off for Russia. The article that she wrote was rejected by Russian censors, and it was never published. Still, Evans' travels in Europe in pursuit of "the story" seem to have stuck with her, and she began to travel to Europe quite regularly, working as a freelance foreign correspondent for publications that included the New York Tribune, The Nation and Asia Magazine. She would later write of her experiences reporting from Moscow during the Russian Revolution as gunfire was exchanged outside her hotel window.
Evans also involved herself with women's suffrage. In the years preceding and following the United States' decision to grant women the vote in 1920, Evans wrote for The Suffragist, an organ of the National Woman's Party, which later changed its name to Equal Rights. She also reported on the suffrage movement in Britain for the Philadelphia Public Ledger.
After the end of World War I, Evans returned to the United States, where she found work as features editor of the Christian Science Monitor. Her responsibilities included buying eleven columns per day, as well as many illustrations, for the paper. Through the mid-1920s she continued to work as a freelance journalist, and wrote articles for The Nation, Century Magazine, the Virginia Quarterly, the Manchester Guardian, and others; she also served as Paris correspondent for Reynolds News Agency. Moreover, during these years she produced the children's book review supplement for The New Republic, which contained articles and reviews by Bertrand Russell, Charles A. Beard, Genevieve Taggard, Babette Deutsch, and Lewis Mumford, among others, including Evans.
During these years Evans also worked at the Whitney Studio Club, a meeting place--founded by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney--for artists living in Greenwich Village. There, Evans learned about painting and becoming involved in the neighborhood's growing art scene. Through her connections at the Whitney Studio Club, Evans was hired as an assistant editor at Coward-McCann, a publishing company whose start-up had also been funded by Whitney. The first book she brought to the firm was a children's title, Wanda Gag's Millions of Cats, a spectacular success which, having sold millions of copies since its publication, is still in print today.
In 1929, Evans authored a book of her own: Frescoes of Diego Rivera, a large-format publication that featured the work of the Mexican artist. Evans, who had previously traveled to Mexico as a reporter for the New York Times, and had written of the working-class appeal of Rivera's work, was responsible for every aspect of the book from start to finish; on its publication, it was the first English-language book on Rivera, and has been cited as a key document in Rivera's rise to popularity in the English-speaking world.
Evans left Coward-McCann in 1930, taking a job with Lippincott, another publishing house. Evans' Lippincott career, like her previous position, allowed her to travel extensively to scout new books. She also oversaw Lippincott's children's publications.
With the rise of the Great Depression, Evans moved to Washington, and went to work for Rexford Tugwell, the head of the Resettlement Administration (RA), an initiative established in 1935, as part of the New Deal, to ease the effects of the Depression on Americans by relocating struggling families to planned communities. Evans pushed for Tugwell to hire the little-known photographer Walker Evans (no relation to Ernestine), who she had previously worked with in her publishing career, to document the RA's accomplishments, believing that both the abject poverty many Americans were enduring, and the government's efforts to allay it, would be best illustrated by photographs. Evans also hired several additional photographers, including Ben Shahn, to undertake similar documentary work for the RA; virtually all of them would go on to enjoy great success as photographers for Life magazine and/or Magnum photo agency. Ernestine Evans was, in addition, responsible for proposing the Works Progress Administration Guides, a series of guidebooks to regions of the United States that were part of the Federal Writers' Project. The project employed hundreds of unemployed writers and researchers, and many of the guides are still in print today.
As the Great Depression ended, Evans returned to her previous occupations of freelance journalist, literary agent, and world traveler. She went to London as a book scout, worked as a researcher for Fortune magazine, and reported on Finland for a "March of Time" newsreel about the country. As World War II began, she returned to the United States. She again went to work for the government in 1943, securing a job with the Office of War Information (OWI). With this position, Evans assisted in efforts to engineer America's image for domestic and foreign audiences. With the large, internationally dispersed network of friends and colleagues that Evans had accumulated, she continued to learn about foreign cultures through her correspondence with friends situated in other places.
From about 1944 until the early 1950s, Evans worked as a book reviewer for the New York Herald Tribune's weekly supplement, but as she grew older fewer writing jobs opened up for her.
Evans died in 1967.
Scope and Content
This collection contains material related to the life of Ernestine Evans and others in her broad network of friends and colleagues. Correspondence, both personal and professional, and literary manuscripts, constitute the bulk of the collection. The majority of the letters date from the 1940s onward; Evans' early correspondence is not a part of this collection. The collection contains dozens of literary manuscripts; most of these probably belong to authors for whom Evans served as literary agent. Evans' own written work is also available here in the form of clippings and other printed material. Moreover, the collection contains a considerable number of personal documents that offer insight into the practicalities of Evans' life, including notebooks, contact lists, passports, medical documents and financial records. Copious photographs on a range of subjects, as well as a variety of mostly unattributed life-drawings and paintings, constitute the considerable array of visual material that this collection also contains.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1912, 1926-1968, Undated
Series II. Writings, 1922-1962, Undated
Series III. Personal, 1907-1968, Undated
Series IV. Visual Material, 1890s-1963, Undated
Subjects
Evans, Ernestine, 1889-1967.; Flaherty, Frances Hubbard.; Flaherty, Robert Joseph, 1884-1951.; Forbes-Robertson, Diana.; Journalism--United States.; Journalists--Correspondence.; Women and journalism.; Women authors, American.; Photographs.; Women journalists.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1968 M-68 Flaherty, Frances Hubbard Gift
1995 Ross G. Harrison, III Gift
Gift of Frances Hubbard Flaherty, 1968.
Gift of Ross G. Harrison, III, 1995
Related Material
Joseph Barnes Papers, 1907-1970, 1923-1970 Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hubert Renfro Knickerbocker Paper, 1914-1950 Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Series I: Correspondence, 1912, 1926-1968, Undated
  This series contains Evans' personal and professional correspondence, and it includes letters both incoming and outgoing. The majority of these letters dates to the 1940s and 1950s; this archive does not contain Evans' early correspondence. Evans' most voluminous correspondence was with Jessie Heckman Hirschl, a lifelong friend whom she met during her undergraduate studies. Other friends and colleagues that are well represented here include: Evans' close friend Frances H. Flaherty, wife of the documentary filmmaker Robert Flaherty. (Evans collaborated with Robert Flaherty on several occasions.); Gertrude Emerson Sen, an expert on Asia, who lived in India and was, like Evans, a member of the Society of Women Geographers; Margaret Barrington (“Topsy”), a writer who lived in Ireland; Helga Greene, a prominent London literary agent; and Karl A. Bickel and Carleton Beals, two writers for whom she served as literary agent. Evans' correspondence also includes letters to and from luminaries that include Walker Evans, Jean Renoir, Cornell Capa and Katherine Anne Porter.
  - Incoming, 1912 1930s-1949, (13 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 12)
  - Incoming, 1950-1959, (11 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 11)
  - Incoming, 1960s, (5 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 5)
  - Incoming, Undated, (6 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 6 to 11)
  - Incoming, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Outgoing, circa 1930s-1967, (6 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 3 to 8)
  - Outgoing, circa 1930s-1967, (5 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 5)
  - Outgoing, 1941-1945, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing--Flaherty, Robert and Frances, circa 1940-1950, (6 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 8 to 13)
  - Outgoing, 1960-1965 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Others, 1932-1958, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 15 to 16)
  - Others, 1932-1958, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Regarding Evans, 1955-1967, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 3 to 4)
  - Fragments, 1941-1965, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Alphabetical and previously catalogued
    - Allen, Evelyn, 1953, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Anderson, Eleanor and Sherwood, 1946-1957, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Barrington, Margaret “Topsy,” 1941-1952, Undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Bickel, Karl, 1941-1954, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Bliven-Sheean, 1941-1945 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Capa, Cornell, Undated (includes reminiscences of Robert Capa) (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Evans, Walker, Undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Flaherty, Robert, Frances and family, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Flaherty, Robert, Frances and family, 1937-1951, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Graham, Eleanor, 1940-1958, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Greene, Helga, 1953-1965, Undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Hirschl, Jessie [Heckman], 1938-1968, Undated, (8 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 4 to 11)
    - Johnstone, Ken, 1959-1961, Undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1940, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Plomer, William, 1943-1958 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - [Porter,] Katherine Anne, 1944-1951, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Schaffner, John to Mr. and Mrs. Richard Edes Harrison, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Sen, Gertrude--Mrs. Basiswar, 1926-1965, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 5 to 6)
    - [Treat Bergeret,] Ida, 1947-1958, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - General, 1941-1958, Undated, (3 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 8 to 10)
- Series II: Writings, 1922-1962, Undated
  Included in this series are manuscripts, drafts, published work and notes by Evans and others; many of the writers whose work appears here were probably Evans' clients during her time as a literary agent. Various manuscripts of Evans' written work are available, including several drafts of an article about Nina Khrushcheva that she wrote during Khrushcheva and her husband's visit to America in 1959, drafts of book reviews, articles for the Office of War Information and various other writings.
  Manuscripts and drafts by other authors include work by Carlton Beals, Martha Bensley Bruère, Clinch Calkins, Elizabeth Ellis, Thomas Hibben, Anabel Hughes, Paula Holladay, Ellen Nelson, James W. Osgood, Ken Sato, Felizia Seyd, Janet Stevenson, Harriet Teague, Beatrice Washburn, Annabel Williams-Ellis, and Corwin Willson, among others.
  Memoranda, transcripts, newspaper and magazine clippings (of Evans' work and others'), and full periodicals and books are also represented.
  - By Evans
    - General, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 11 to 12)
    - Book Reviews, Undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Finland--for Esso Magazine, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Nina Khrushcheva, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - “Looking East from Moscow”--for Asia magazine, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - “The Man at the Corner Table,” manuscript, Undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - “A New Name in Lights: Gertrud Scholtz-Klink,” circa 1936 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Office of War Information, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - “The War of Ideas”--for the Herald Tribune, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Writings on World Religion, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Untitled manuscript, Undated, chapters 1-11 (2 Folders) (Box 9, Box 4-5)
  - By others
    - Authorship Unknown
      - Children’s Fables, Undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Children’s Literature, Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - "Conversion of Exigency," Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Germany, Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - History of Grace Abbott and U.S. Children’s Bureau, Undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Irish-American History, Undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Korea, circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Poetry, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - The Seventh Continent, Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Tilly, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Vegetables, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - The Wedding Trip, Undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Who Is Growing Older? Everybody!, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 6 to 7)
      - General--Manuscripts, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 8 to 9)
      - General--Fragments, Undated, (1 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - General--Fragments, Undated, (9 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1 to 9)
    - Augur, Helen--various, Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Beals, Carlton-- Flower of France, Undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Beals, Carolyn Kennedy-- The Trial Begins, Undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Boehm, Carson-- Oceanography, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Boyd, Madeleine-- Claude Monet, Undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Bruère, Martha Bensley and Robert Bruère-- The Triumph of Felicity Brail: An American Parable, (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 6 to 7)
    - Calkins, Clinch-- State Occasion, Undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Craton, Anne Washington--untitled, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Ellis, Elizabeth-- The Fatal Diet, Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Grierson, John-- Propaganda and Education, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Hibben, Thomas-- Rammed Earth Construction, 1940, Undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Holladay, Paula-- Call Me Hagar, Undated (incomplete) (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Holladay, Paula--“Prolegomena” to “The Journey Homeward,” Undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Holladay, Paula--various, Undated (2 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 6 to 7)
    - Holmes, Winifred--poetry--“The Red Sea Dolphins,” 1945 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Hughes, Anabel--Poetry--Drafts and Notes, Undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Jarecka, Louise--Journal, circa 1931 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Leland, Marine-- French Canada, 1944-1945 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Lovett, Robert Morss--“The Outside Children – The Virgins,” 1942 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Momoko, Ishii--“Merry Dolls, Quiet Dolls,” Undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Morrison, Stanley-- The Bibliography of Newspapers and the Writing of History, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Nelson, Ellen-- Dodo the Duck, Undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Osgood, James W.-- A Constructive Program for Conservatives, Undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Sato, Ken-- The Yellow Jap Dogs, Undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Sen, Gertrude-- Testing Ground in NEFA, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Seyd, Felizia-- Alexander I of Russia, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Shapley, Olive--untitled manuscript, 1949-1950 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Stevenson, Jane-- Kate: A Play, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Teague, Harriet-- Richard Mill: In Memoriam, Undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Thompson, Dorothy--“Editorial for Ladies’ Home Journal,” Undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Tikhonov, Nikolai-- Tales of Leningrad, Undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Treat, Ida--Manuscripts, Undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Turner, Roger-- If I must go down to the sea again, Undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Uht, John-- Four Tigers, Four Trees and Mabu, Undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Washburn, Beatrice--Short Pieces, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Washburn, Beatrice-- Sketches of Mexico-- Manchester Guardian, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Williams-Ellis, Annabel-- Human Nature Study for Schools, Undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Willson, Corwin-- Merrily We Roll, 1962, (3 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 2 to 4)
    - Woodward, Anne-- Paddy Corrigan Stories, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Wuolijoki, Hella-- Women of Property, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Children’s Book Manuscripts
      - Barrington, Margaret, 1946, Undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Jarecka, Louise, Undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - General, Undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Various Authors, A-Y, Undated (6 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 1 to 6)
    - Project files--Greeting Cards, Undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Project files--General, Undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Memos and Press Releases
    - BBC Fortnightly Newsletter, 1942 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - British Information Services, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - George Eastman House, 1949, Undated (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Journal of the American Medical Association, 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Lend Lease: Miss Rankin’s Amendment, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Magnum Photo, 1955-1959 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Palmer, Frederick, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Penguin Books, Undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Post Office Department, 1946-1958 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - UNESCO World Review, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - General, 1944-1957, Undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Notes
    - Biographical, Undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Women Journalists, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - General, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 9 to 10)
  - Printed Material
    - Books
      - General, Undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Cockade Portfolio, V. I. Lenin, Undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Ellen Browning Scripps, 1936 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Encyclopedia Britannica--Picture Books, Undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - From Learning to Earning, The Welsh, Undated (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - Children and Their Books, edited by Evans, 1926 (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - Collection by Evans, circa 1928-1940 (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - Lasten Kesä, Undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Clippings
      - Eleanor Anderson, Undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Manchester Guardian, 1948 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Newspaper Articles by Evans, 1945-1953, Undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Magazine Articles by Evans, circa 1920s-1949 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Reviews by Evans, Undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - General, Undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Pamphlets
      - Alfred University, 1942-1943 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - Children’s Literature, 1939-1960 (Box 23, Folder 8)
      - Lamont, Corliss--“The Myth of Soviet Aggression,” “Challenge to McCarthy,” 1953-1954 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - Medical, 1947, Undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
      - Scottish independence, 1944-1946 (Box 23, Folder 11)
      - United States Children’s Bureau, 1937-1962 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Periodicals
      - Fair Winds magazine, 1937-1939 (Box 23, Folder 13)
      - Trade Magazines: Advertising Typographers Association of America, Schlumberger, Standard Oil, 1952-1957 (Box 23, Folder 14)
      - General, 1941-1958 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Transcripts
    - “Woman’s Hour,” 1949 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Library of Congress Hearings, 1954 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - The Hollywood Story,” 1948 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Proposals, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Subject Files
    - Film, 1944-1948, Undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Finland, Undated (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Missionaries of Batanga, Phillipines, Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Office of War Information, 1938-1944 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Series III: Personal, 1907-1968, Undated